I wouldn't want to be torine right now.
Talk about bad publicity. Torine is an
amino acid, a molecule that we produce
as well as consume. And although last
year and the year before was the year of
torine with multiple studies coming out
indicating it being a molecule of youth,
this year it's taken its lumps. One
study linked it to cancer, which we
already covered, and a new study calls
into question whether torine really is a
molecule of youth. This one I have to
admit they provide convincing evidence
that we'll get into and even so we can
mount a protor torine resistance based
in science. Here's the conundrum. A huge
extremely influential study released a
few years ago that showed all kinds of
ways that torine is linked to reversing
and improving symptoms of aging. They
showed it across multiple animal models,
including some closer to humans,
monkeys. Beyond that they had evidence
torine declines precipitously with age
in humans. We can see that here. On the
vertical axis we have the blood torine
levels. On the horizontal axis we have
age and a line going through the data
indicates the trend of the data and
clearly it drops significantly from
birth. So based on this association
along with a mountain of data on
supplementing torine showing life
extension effects improvements in
multiple organ systems from bone,
muscle, brain and more. It was perfectly
reasonable to assume that torine was a
molecule that we needed to replace as
we'd likely become deficient over time.
So keep that association in mind. As we
age, torine levels decline.
Unfortunately, this new study provides
direct convincing evidence that is not
true. In fact, not only is it not true,
but it may actually be the opposite.
What do I mean? If we pop open this
study, the researchers took blood
samples from three groups of people
between ages 26 to 100. If we pop open
that data, we again see torine levels on
the vertical axis and age on the
horizontal. You'll immediately notice
that we don't see that precipitous drop
that we did in the previous influential
torine study. The left pink graph is
women and the right blue graph is men.
In fact, if you squint, you see that
torine levels rise over the lifespan. In
fact, the same was true of monkeys and
mice. Here's the monkey data. You can
see a pretty noticeable curve upwards in
the later years directly in opposition
of what we knew before. So, what's going
on here? Did the previous researchers
deceive us or was it an error that was
made? Well, they didn't deceive us, nor
did they make an error. at least not
experimental error. This initial study
measured touring in a crosssectional
format. That means that they measured a
person at one time point in their life,
let's say 30 years old, and they
measured another person at one point in
their life, say 64 years old, and then
they compared. That's what led to these
results. Now, that seems pretty
reasonable, and you'd expect to detect a
real association. However, a better way
to go about things is longitudinally, as
in you measure a person at 30 and then
you measure the same person at 40 and
then 50 and so on. That way, you're
controlling naturally for many more
factors like genetics, life
circumstances, living location,
potentially diet, and so on. That's the
method that this new study did it. So,
this is a prime example of knowing the
limitations of study design. Just when
we think that one type of study design
is sufficient to answer a question, a
better study design indicates otherwise.
That means the new study is probably
correct. Touring does not decline with
age. But does that then mean that torine
doesn't matter? Well, not quite. From
the same study, if we look at the
relationship between serum torine and
leg strength, the torine levels are on
the vertical axis and the increase in
leg strength measured as knee strength
is on the horizontal. In women, there's
an association with greater blood torine
levels being associated with better leg
strength. So there's some indication
that torine is still related to
important health metrics. But if we look
at something like I don't know grip
strength, we no longer see an
association. So it is specific to the
experiment. There's a lot of these kinds
of nuances like how age affects these
muscle data and the torine levels in the
organs and some additional data on
weight and torine. I'll be covering that
in the full analysis included for the
Physionic Insiders. If you're interested
in learning all that there is along with
discussing in live sessions with me,
getting a private podcast access, and
much more, check out the Physionic
Insiders. It's linked in the description
box. Now, while there might be some
signals that is still important, I don't
know about you, but I'm pretty
distrustful of these simple associative
data, especially when we're getting
mixed results. Fortunately, when
discussing metrics like strength, guess
what? We don't even need to rely on
associative data. We can skip it
entirely and go straight to the
questions like if I consume torine, will
I see improvements in muscle
performance, which are easily answered
by intervention studies, or as some
people like to shout,
lay Norton, randomized control trials.
So taking a cursory peek at a study on
torine. If we pop open muscle strength
results compared against a group not
consuming torine, we can see that torine
indicates benefit as torine condition
maintains muscle strength while the
non-torrine placebo group does not.
Clearly there's a benefit. This is
further corroborated in systematic
reviews as well. Although not all
studies indicate benefit beyond muscle
strength and performance. We've covered
several studies directly implicating
torine in improving a variety of
conditions like metabolic syndrome. So
to say that torine is useless now simply
because it doesn't decrease with age
just doesn't speak to the actual cause
and effect studies that were performed.
None of those care about your
associative torine levels. All they show
is that from multiple groups of people
torine supplementation provides mild to
moderate benefits at least on the
outcomes that we briefly discussed. So
the takeaway here is one that blood
torine levels may not decline with age
as we initially thought. Two, this
reality does not mean that torine is not
beneficial when supplemented at least
based on the current intervention study
literature. In fact, let's imagine that
you don't believe me. What if I tried to
convince you with some more direct
evidence on Torine's use right Here.